A Guide to the Stanislaw Makielski Papers, 1914-1968
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Stanislaw Makielski Papers 1914-1968
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10768-c
This collection consists of 1069 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These drawings and related materials were given to the University of Virginia Library by Ms. Jane Dandridge of Charlottesville, Virginia, on June 30, 1988.
Scope and Content Information
This collection contains additional architectural drawings of Charlottesville architect and member of the architecture faculty at the University of Virginia, Stanislaw John Makielski (1893-1969), and consists of 1,019 architectural drawings and ca. fifty other items (25 oversize folders), 1914-1968, and undated. These include drawings of central Virginia residences, churches, other institutions and businesses; fraternities; instructional drawings of construction; University of Virginia buildings and renovations; and normal & industrial schools in the South. Other architects represented in this collection include Frederick Nichols, Richard Phillips Fox, Louis Justement, and Fiske Kimball. The drawings have been grouped into the following categories: schools (folders 1-2); churches (folder 3); residences (folders 4-13); businesses, institutions, & miscellaneous (folders 14-16); fraternities (folder 17); University of Virginia related (folders 18-23, including part of folder 12); drawings of Richard Phillips Fox (folder 24); and instructional drawings (folder 25). Also present is one folder of supporting correspondence, small drawings, photographs, and specifications for some of Makielski's projects.
These projects include the residence of Conrad C. Fernsell, Albemarle County; the residence of Professor Orland E. White, Charlottesville; the Blue Ridge Industrial School, Bris, Greene County, Virginia; photographs concerning City Hall, Charlottesville; the Crozet Methodist Church, Crozet, Virginia; the residence of Mr. & Mrs. Green Peyton, Albemarle County; McGregor Motors Company Building; Mission Home, Standardsville, Virginia; the residence of Lester J. Cappon, Charlottesville; Gailor Industrial School, Mason, Tennessee; the University of Virginia Experimental Laboratory; the Fort Valley Normal & Industrial School, Fort Valley, Georgia; the Hoffman St. Mary Normal & Industrial School, Mason, Tennessee; the residence of Thomas Fitzhugh; and the Okolona Normal & Industrial School, Okolona, Mississippi.
Contents List
- Schools
  - Gaudet Normal & Industrial School, New Orleans, Louisiana, #450 1946-1945, 19 sheets (Folder 1)
  - Gailor Industrial School, Mason, Tennessee #425 1939-1945, 11 sheets (Folder 1)
  - Hoffman St. Mary Normal & Industrial School, Mason, Tennessee #425 1930-1935, 18 sheets (Folder 1)
  - Fort Valley College, Fort Valley, Georgia, #520 1925-1941, 14 sheets (Folder 1)
    Includes Fort Valley High & Industrial School #447 (1 sheet), and Ludlow & Peabody (3 sheets).
  - Okolona Normal & Industrial School, Okolona, Mississippi #433 1933-1945, 21 sheets (Folder 2)
  - Blue Ridge Industrial School Chapel, Dyke, Green County, Virginia, # 428 1928-1930, 25 sheets (Folder 2)
  - Blue Ridge Industrial School Boy's Dormitory & Residence, [Bris.], Virginia, #428 & # 436 1930-1932, 13 sheets (Folder 2)
  - Blue Ridge Industrial School, Dyke, Green County, or [Bris.?], Virginia #506, #509, #535, & #537 1938-1945, 11 sheets (Folder 2)
- Churches
  - Crozet Methodist Church, Crozet, Virginia #687 1961, 13 sheets (Folder 3)
  - Preventorium, Mission Home, Standardsville, Virginia, Miss Anne Parks #431 1931-1932, 18 sheets (Folder 3)
  - Christ Church, Lancaster County, Virginia, by Frederick D. Nichols 1960, 14 sheets (Folder 3)
  - Church of the Holy Comforter, Charlottesville, Virginia #338 1924-1966, 35 sheets (Folder 3)
- Residences
  - Lester J. Cappon, Charlottesville, Virginia #524 1940-1941, 17 sheets (Folder 4)
  - Mr. & Mrs. Robert T. Barbee, Charlottesville, Virginia, unnumbered 1965, 8 sheets (Folder 4)
  - Professor Linwood Lehman, University of Virginia, #352 1927, 13 sheets (Folder 4)
  - Mr. & Mrs. James K. Barr, Albemarle County, Virginia #424 1931-1947, 18 sheets (Folder 5)
  - Mr. & Mrs. James McCahill, Charlottesville, Virginia [#352 ?] 1962, 5 sheets (Folder 5)
  - Clifton Waller Barrett, Farmington, Albemarle County, Virginia 1961, 7 sheets (Folder 5)
  - Conrad C. Fernsell, Albemarle County, Virginia #331 1927-1928, 11 sheets (Folder 5)
  - James F. Dulaney, Rugby Road, Charlottesville, Virginia #678 1959-1960, 9 sheets (Folder 6)
  - Mrs. C.L. Luman, Crozet, Virginia #543 1946-1947, 24 sheets (Folder 6)
  - Professor Orland E. White, Charlottesville, Virginia #437 1931-1932, 7 sheets (Folder 6)
  - Professor Hugh Spencer, Charlottesville, Virginia #574 n.d., 2 sheets (Folder 7)
  - Dr. G.W. Crutchfield, Charlottesville, Virginia #539 1942, 4 sheets (Folder 7)
  - Mr. & Mrs. O.J. Hale, University of Virginia #449 1936, 8 sheets (Folder 7)
  - Miss Doris Woodward, Albemarle County, Virginia #512 1938, 3 sheets (Folder 7)
  - Dr. W.M. Forrest, Cuckoo, Virginia #510 1938, 6 sheets (Folder 7)
  - Alfred Burger, Albemarle County, Virginia #515 1938-1939, 7 sheets (Folder 7)
  - N.W. Larkum, Albemarle County, Virginia #514 1938, 3 sheets (Folder 7)
  - R.W. Witcher, [Charlottesville, Virginia ?] #671 1957, 1 sheet (Folder 7)
  - Unidentified #511 1938, 3 sheets (Folder 7)
  - Dwelling for Arthudious Haden, Charlottesville, Virginia #672 1958, 1 sheet (Folder 7)
  - Residence for Miss B.J. Watson #576 1946, 1 sheet (Folder 7)
  - Gateway to Residence of W. Carl Whitlock, Gildersleeve Wood #381 1930, 1 sheet (Folder 7)
  - Residence for Professor S. Vernon McCasland, Charlottesville, Virginia #533 1941, 1 sheet (Folder 7)
  - Details of House No. 1, Goshen, Rockbridge County, Virginia #402 1928, 1 sheet (Folder 7)
  - Russell Mott, Charlottesville, Virginia #406 1928-1929, 10 sheets (Folder 8)
    See also folder 9.
  - Russell Mott, Charlottesville, Virginia #406 1929, 7 sheets (Folder 9)
    See also folder 8.
  - Dr. R.W. Roberts, Charlottesville, Virginia #586 1948, 15 sheets (Folder 9)
  - Elias R. Newman, Charlottesville, Virginia #386 1928, 13 sheets (Folder 9)
  - E.M. Leake, Charlottesville, Virginia #549 n.d., 2 sheets (Folder 9)
  - Frederick Wood, Charlottesville, Virginia #604 1950, 2 sheets (Folder 9)
  - J.E. Berdahl, Charlottesville, Virginia #579 1946, 3 sheets (Folder 9)
  - Thomas Perkins Abernethy, Albemarle County, Virginia #508 1938, 8 sheets (Folder 10)
  - J. Allan Battle, Albemarle County, Virginia #544 1943, 1961, 8 sheets (Folder 10)
  - Mr. & Mrs. Green Peyton, Albemarle County, Virginia #448 1937, 4 sheets (Folder 10)
  - Mr. & Mrs. Robert C. Walker, Albemarle County, Virginia #642 1955, 3 sheets (Folder 10)
  - Lyndon Small, Charlottesville, Virginia #507 1937-1938, 3 sheets (Folder 10)
  - Harvey A. Basham, Prospect Hill, Charlottesville, Virginia #405 1929-1932, 45 sheets (Folder 11)
  - Albert G.A. Balz, Charlottesville, Virginia #335 1925-1926, 15 sheets (Folder 12)
  - Albert H. Morrill, Keene, Virginia #339 1926, 2 sheets (Folder 12)
  - Thomas Fitzhugh, University of Virginia by Fiske Kimball & Stanislaw Makielski #400 1928, 35 sheets (Folder 13)
- Businesses, Institutions & Miscellaneous
  - L.D. Harlow Apartment Building, Charlottesville, Virginia #564 1945-1947, 15 sheets (Folder 14)
  - Louisa County Memorial Medical Service Center, Louisa, Virginia #676 1959, 6 sheets (Folder 14)
  - House for the Loyal Order of Moose, Charlottesville, Virginia #608 1951, 2 sheets (Folder 14)
  - MacGregor Motors Inc., Charlottesville, Virginia #563 1941-1947, 16 sheets (Folder 14)
  - The Jefferson Institute, Warsaw, Poland #546 1944, 10 sheets (Folder 15)
  - Westerly Motor Court, Mr. & Mrs. Charles L. Goodloe, Albemarle County, Virginia #662 1956, 10 (Folder 15)
  - W.M. Mayo, Jr., Commercial Building, Albemarle County, Virginia, unnumbered 1965, 9 sheets (Folder 15)
  - City Hall, Charlottesville, Virginia, #562 1945, 9 sheets (Folder 15)
  - Albemarle Motor Company, Charlottesville, Virginia, Alterations & Additions #411 1929, 14 sheets (Folder 16)
  - Chancellor Building Alterations & Additions for Howard B. Cook, Charlottesville, Virginia #334 1926-1927, 14 sheets (Folder 16)
  - Lewis Apartments, for Herbert Harris, Charlottesville, Virginia #550 1944-1945, 5 sheets (Folder 16)
  - Filling Station for A.F. Dulaney #416 1927, 2 sheets (Folder 16)
- Fraternities
  - Phi Gamma Delta, University of Virginia #385 1928-1929, n.d., 24 sheets (Folder 17)
  - Phi Kappa Psi, University of Virginia #356 1928, 14 sheets (Folder 17)
  - Sigma Nu, University of Virginia, #250, by Louis Justement (8 sheets) and Additions by Stanislaw Makielski, # 696 1927, 1963, 16 sheets (Folder 17)
- University of Virginia
  - Blandy Experimental Farm, Boyce, Virginia #531 1940-1941, 40 sheets (Folder 18)
  - Blandy Experimental Farm, Boyce, Virginia #531 1940-1941, 28 sheets (Folder 19)
  - Mountain Lake Biological Station, Giles County, Virginia #438 1931-1932, 12 sheets (Folder 20)
  - Levering Hall & House "F," University of Virginia #607 1951-1954, 9 sheets (Folder 20)
  - Bursar's Office, University of Virginia #605 1950, 2 sheets (Folder 20)
  - Scott Stadium, University of Virginia, Ticket Booths #587 and Toilets #601 1948-1950, 7 sheets each (Folder 20)
  - Piedmont Apartments, University of Virginia, unnumbered, by Frederick Nichols n.d., 9 sheets (Folder 20)
  - Greenhouse for Miller School of Biology #615 1952-1962, 5 sheets (Folder 21)
  - Monroe Hall Alterations #NM-5 1961-1962, 4 sheets (Folder 21)
  - Newcomb Hall Parking Lot Plot Plan & Step Study, Department of Buildings & Grounds, unnumbered 1959, 4 sheets (Folder 21)
  - Northwest Newcomb Hall Terrace Stairs #680 1960, 1 sheet (Folder 21)
  - Brooks Museum Alterations #588 1949, 2 sheets (Folder 21)
  - Alterations to the College Bookstore #548 1944, 5 sheets (Folder 21)
  - Incinerator for the Medical Center #688 1961-1962, 2 sheets (Folder 21)
  - The Rotunda Interior Details #518 1950, 3 sheets (Folder 21)
  - Dormitories Entrance Doors #593 1949, 1953, 1 sheet (Folder 21)
  - Take Down Stage Platform Plans & Details # 595 1949, 1 sheet (Folder 21)
  - Peabody Hall West Doorway #597 1950, 1 sheet (Folder 21)
  - Maintainance Building Heating Plans #596 1949, 1 sheet (Folder 21)
  - Student's Observatory Plans, Section, Elevations, & Details #599 1950, 2 sheets (Folder 21)
  - Washington Hall Office Partitions, unnumbered 1951, 1 sheet (Folder 21)
  - Clemons House Revisions to Bath & Facilities, unnumbered 1950, 1 sheet (Folder 21)
  - Randall Hall Alterations & Additions, unnumbered 1950, 1 sheet (Folder 21)
  - "Pedestal" for the Bust of John L. Newcomb, Alderman Library, unnumbered 1950, 1 sheet (Folder 21)
  - Leander McCormick Observatory Sewage System, unnumbered n.d., 3 sheets (Folder 21)
  - Pavilion No. 1, Rear Balcony & Steps, unnumbered 1950, 2 sheets (Folder 21)
  - New Academic Building South Approaches #621 1952, 3 sheets (Folder 21)
  - The [Alpha Rho Chi] House Sketch, unnumbered 1950, 1 sheet (Folder 22)
  - University Commons Vestibule for Central Doors, Plans & Details, unnumbered 1951, 1 sheet (Folder 22)
  - Engineering Building Door & Frame Moisture Room, unnumbered 1949, 1 sheet (Folder 22)
  - Mechanics Housing Apartments #600 1950, 1 sheet (Folder 22)
  - New Shops Interior Details, Offices, Pay & Observation Window #603 1950, 2 sheets (Folder 22)
  - Cabell Hall Exhaust Louvre #612 1952, 1 sheet (Folder 22)
  - Peabody Hall Offices #617 1952, 1 sheet (Folder 22)
  - Chapel Panel #618 1952, 1 sheet (Folder 22)
  - University of Virginia Hospital, Alterations to BSMT of the South Wing of the Medical Building, Plans for Research Division Department of Surgery #619 1953, 1 sheet (Folder 22)
  - Minor Hall Alterations for Major Kaufman #622 1953, 1 sheet (Folder 22)
  - University of Virginia Hospital, Department of Microbiology, Alterations & Additions #623 1953, 5 sheets (Folder 22)
  - University of Virginia Hospital, Alteration to Office #624 1953, 2 sheets (Folder 22)
  - University of Virginia Hospital, Neuro Psychiatric Ward Special Heating #631 1953, 1 sheet (Folder 22)
  - University of Virginia Hospital Pharmacy Alterations #633 1954, 1 sheet (Folder 22)
  - University of Virginia Hospital Admissions Offices #634 1954, 1 sheet (Folder 22)
  - University of Virginia Dormitory Alteration to Kitchen Exhaust System for the "Castle" #635 1954, 1 sheet (Folder 22)
  - University of Virginia Hospital Alterations to "C" Ward & "F" Ward Diet Kitchens #636 1954, 2 sheets (Folder 22)
  - Cobb Chemical Laboratory Distilled Water System #639 1954, 1 sheet (Folder 22)
  - Thornton Hall Dean's Offices & Alterations to Building "C" #640 1954, 4 sheets (Folder 23)
  - Fayerweather Hall Lecture Rooms and Materials & Filing Cases #643 1953-1956, 4 sheets (Folder 23)
  - Cobb Chemistry Building Additions #645 1954-1955, 2 sheets (Folder 23)
  - Library for Graduate School of Business Administration, Monroe Hall #650 1955, 3 sheets (Folder 23)
  - Clark Memorial Hall, Law Building Office Partition D #651 1955, 1 sheet (Folder 23)
  - Booster Pump Station for the University of Virginia #653 1955, 1 sheet (Folder 23)
  - Minor Hall Alterations #656 1955, 1 sheet (Folder 23)
  - Warehouse for Purchasing Department #681 1959-1960, 6 sheets (Folder 23)
  - Computer Center, Physics Building #684 1960, 2 sheets (Folder 23)
  - Field House for Lambeth Field [#444] n.d., 1 sheet (Folder 23)
  - Additions & Alterations to the Electrical Engineering Lab #706 1968, 8 sheets (Folder 23)
  - The Rotunda Restoration # 518 1938, 11 sheets (Folder 23)
- RICHARD PHILLIPS FOX (NEWARK, DELAWARE) DRAWINGS
  - Residence for Mr. & Mrs. William F. Burkley, Ricketts Mill Road, Elkton, Maryland #6224 1963, 16 sheets (Folder 24)
  - Residence for Mr. & Mrs. Gerald J. Risser, New Street Road, West Goshen Township, Chester County, West Chester, Pennsylvania #6102 1961-1962, 24 sheets (Folder 24)
- INSTRUCTIONAL DRAWINGS - CONSTRUCTION
  - Truss Design, Frame Construction, Semi-Fire Proof Construction Details 1939-1940, 24 sheets (Folder 25)
  - Spandrel Sections, Mill Construction, & Masonry Bridge 1914-1915, 4 sheets (Folder 25)